so this is a Suitor
of the San mutinikaya and it's in
regards to
celibacy
and this conversation takes place
between a king and a Baku named Venable
pindola
and the King goes up to this Monk
and you ask him what is the cause and
the reason
why these other young monks these bikers
uh
young young boys with black hair endowed
with the blessing of Youth in the prime
of their life who have not played with
Central Pleasures leave the complete and
pure holy life all all their lives and
maintain it continuously
and Venable pindola he answers great
king this was said by the blessed one
who knows and sees
come because towards women old enough to
be your mother set up the idea that they
are your mother
towards those of an age to be your
sisters set up the idea that they are
your sisters so towards those young
enough to be your daughters set up the
idea that they are your daughters
this is the cause and the reason why
these young diggers lead the complete
and pure holy life all their lives and
maintain it continuously
and the King says the mind is wanton so
you know given to lust and unsatisfied
sometimes states of lust arise even
towards women old enough to be one's
mother sometimes they rise towards the
women of an age to be one sister
or one's daughter
is there any cause and reason why these
young begus
lead to complete and is there any other
cause and reason why these young bikers
lead a complete and pure early life all
their lives and maintain it continuously
and he gives the other
a few other causes but uh
just this reason first
so a person has to
you know consider
other people as
you know your mother your father but
your sister
your friend your son your daughter
so as to
maybe give you a sense of shame or make
you a bit more respectful and not see
them in that light of a
sexual partner
yeah but see as it says it you know you
they would establish an idea
in other words they would set up a
context but in order to be able
but in order to be able
for that idea to become a context that
will prevent you to have a luster Rising
you need to have been withdrawn and
centrally strained already
like the Mind need to have developed to
some extent because otherwise people
might have an idea they will ask for the
duration of the thought
and then the context goes with the
thought where the idea is gone so then
the last comes back and takes over and
becomes first
so it's something you need to frequently
think about pondering when you're not
lustful and develop that as a state of
mind that whomever you're relating to is
through these Frameworks of mother
sister daughter
friend um
um
like The Compassion same it's kind of
similar to the primary heart as you set
up a state of mind through like
frequently recollecting and thinking
about it up until those values are
established and then they need to be
protected yeah but if you expect to just
have this idea magically take over you
and then prevent loss from arising
just because you thought of it that way
no it won't last
my last initial is a novelty of a new
thing but then you're just going to
become dry abstraction where you try to
force yourself to think but like lust is
still there first
so a person might be lustful towards
another person
and then
they think well let me consider this
person who I'm lusting after as my
mother yeah
yeah it's just going to be as I said
trying to manage the problem first you
need to be recognizing the the the the
state of last the lustful mind should
not be acted out of and then when the
last is not present
you know when you haven't acted out of
it you have to subside
then you start pondering and and you
know like when there's a danger in it
and establishing the ideas they can help
you then later not have uh last night
arise but it's not just it's not on the level
but it's not just it's not on the level
of an antidote it's on the level of
developing your mind
even before the last is there so again
in order to to set up the idea that can
then endure as a context that will
prevent you to be lustful towards this
person or that person you need to have
seen your mind
you need to have understood it
so you need to have been practicing well
exactly there's a there's a certain
order of the gradual training it's not
like yeah it I can make sense of it let
me just do it now you'll be doing it for
wrong reasons so and people exactly
would be trying to paste and and almost
maintain these thoughts like
mechanically as a mantra do not have
lust no that's not setting up the idea
establishing the dhamma the presence of
the phenomenon this is the framework
where people will be regarded in such
manner which is not conducive for lust
not increasing and so on but if you put
the last first then yeah
even even mother sister daughter doesn't
matter the the mind will be attracted
through lust
so you have to have you know restraint
beforehand
you're making that decision no
difficulty with it yes yeah getting some
benefit Clarity yeah I think you need to
practice towards the Right View first
yeah because otherwise everything else will
because otherwise everything else will
be just rooted in you mistaking the
practice of dhamma I uprooting of the
existence and the problem for managing
so this would be just another novelty
way to manage these disturbing states of
mind
but you can see that this is for just
helping it developed mind already
yeah of course my mind that's that's
Daddy has Right View so now personally
this is the mind or what it is and can
relate to it in the right manner not act
out of it and try to manage it but
actually can endure it in order to
approach it
as we say so often then yeah of course
then such ideas perceptions
contemplations themes of course they are
very beneficial because they'll be done
on the right basis for the right reasons
they have to sort of a clean the mind in
a broad you know yes covering all bases
yeah
so that one can live live the celibate
life fully one's whole life as it says
you know um
but as this King says he says his mind
is so
you know wanton hmm
that even
it can have attraction to the mother of
the daughter because the last two we put
first the last two mine would be first
all the ideas would be secondary
attractions and so this is what other
reason do these monks live such a good
holy life complete
and he says breaking this was said by
the blessed one
Pickers reviewed this very body upwards
from the soles of the feet downwards
from the tips of the hairs enclosed in
skin as full of many kinds of impurities
as full of many kinds of impurities
there are these they are in this body
head hairs sinews flesh bone
contents of the stomach excrement and so
on so before we go further exactly so
review this so people often confuse that
as do the body sweeping of this
visualizations and so on and sensations
of head to toe now review those things
you can't see insides of your body
so review them reflexively
because those are factual things that
your body is made of
so in other words it's another context
that you established another set of
ideas that is suitable and not that is
suitable for non-last and not suitable
for last if established correctly in the
right order
that's why even that people would do
these reviewings and so on on the level
of just like a as I said abstract ideas
of brain bile this this almost like like
Mantra chanting the same as as they were
doing the monasteries but it's like
that's not reviewing it
that's not seeing it on the right level
that you are having already you've
already taken this body
so through your ownership of the body
then start reflecting of that body that
you own mistakenly show but the mistake
is real as such
as made out of these things so that you
experience this passion towards what you
own it's not just some random kind of
abidama commentary style of just just go
through the list of what the body is and
repeat it and somehow it's beautiful in
your mind and some invisible
subconscious levels
no the one the main problem for giving
into lust and engaging with with uh
objects of your sense perceptions
um
is that you're taking this body as yours
pleasurable agreeable suitable uh
accessible to to get pleasure through
and so on they're beautiful you're not
seeing the danger of it beautiful yeah
friendly yours
in your favor and not and it's not any
of those things
so yes you can again if you don't see
your mind if you don't have the right
view all of this will be just another way of
all of this will be just another way of
managing you will be just telling to
yourself what the body is and it would
have like a partial result as I said
with the novelty but sooner or let you
get used to it and the last comes back
first and nothing has really changed
so you need to do it on that level of
not life or I'm doing these observations
of the body first you need to see what
your body is
as in your experience as a whole what is
this body
not like what I observed on account of
already having the body
what is the necessary basis for my
observation of anything
it's the flesh the brain he has a
presence of this thing yeah so do I have
to look at the characteristic see by
understanding what your body is in this
manner you're actually seeing the signs
of your mind already because that's
where the mind is it's that background
it's that peripheral
that cannot be that which cannot be
directly attended to so in this case
true or the object so to speak you are
still doing the same thing you're still
actually uncovering the the
characteristics of that enduring mind
which is in separate from the enduring
body
so yes review it don't leave any part of
it as
of that basis for the world that you
perceive for the desires that you have
for the joys and miseries and so on
don't leave any basis of that background
enduring body that you are here and now
don't leave any of that basis that's not
thoroughly reflected upon as not yours
not suitable a DOT filled with
impurities and so on
because if you do to that extent the
last will still have a footing
and you can reflect on other people's
body again
again
on that peripheral concrete basis not as
a as a second hand kind of abstraction
yes yes
if you reflect on other people's bodies
is so that again you're seeing yourself
through the same form
you don't leave that part out yeah yeah
so you you don't leave yourself out when
reflecting on other bodies so you have
to keep that that correct relationship
between your point of view and the body
you're looking at you're not taking it
as an observation method or another
observation object you're taking it as a
reflection theme that undermines your
point of view of ownership that regards
this body gratuitously as pleasant and
agreeable so it's a very different thing you would
so it's a very different thing you would
go about it very differently
and The Suitor goes on it says so
so
the biku says you know reflect on your
review your body these different parts
and so on
and the King says
that is quite easy for those because who
are developed in body developed in
virtue developed in mind developed in
wisdom but is it difficult for those
beakers who are undeveloped in body
virtue mind and wisdom
sometimes though one thinks I will
attend to the body as foul as disgusting
one beholds it as beautiful
is there any other reason why these
young beakers lead the complete and pure
holy life all their lives
so he said that it's possible for those
that are developed in virtue in the body
and the Right View
but if not then you'll be again so it's
quite a dangerous perversion what it is
anything is like that's what I mean like
um
unless people realize what comes first
and the Right View comes first
The Virtue sense restraint Solitude and
the Right View come first if not you'll
be taking things that don't apply to you
because you don't have the right View
and thinking you are practicing the dumb
so then it's quite dangerous because
again why would you then look on how to
start practicing the Dharma I get the
right view when you're already thinking
of and have a view that you're
practicing the Dharma by doing all these
things that you did in the suitors and
there's so many of them
there's that other Suitor with a monk is
in a cemetery and he in that channel
ground where they're brilliant bodies
and he sees a discarded body of a young
woman and
and
as he was there reflecting on the body
he became lustful towards it so it's
like he was he was seeing you know it's
almost like they had a super practice
he's staring at dead bodies and so on
and then
yeah it needs to be done on the right
level yeah it needs to be done on the
level of the context of what am I doing
not on the level of I will just look at
this and I will do the work for me
initially when you get there maybe the
shocking value or something of something
you don't want to look at but again the
mind would last might not flee from us
we'll get used to it we'll get used to
anything and we'll then perpetuate its
life towards it
doesn't mean it's endless yeah because
it's the framework it's not in the
things you're looking or avoiding from
looking it's in the attitude of the mind it's
it's in the attitude of the mind it's
what you put first it's in desire for
pleasure and not seeing the danger of it
and so on
foreign
yes there is this is what better one
said because dwell guarding the doors of the
because dwell guarding the doors of the
sense faculties having a seen a form of
the eye do not grasp at its signs and
features since if you leave the I faculty
since if you leave the I faculty
unguarded evil and wholesome states of
covetousness and displeasure Mighty
vague practice the way of its restraint
so
he just goes on saying well
essential strength so you can see that
he keeps basically lowering the bar so
to speak
firstly was just the context of how to
regard people you might be attracted to
sustain that you're fine it's like okay
yeah but that's too much to do what else
can a person who can't do that do well
take the context of your own body as
foul is repulsive yeah okay but even
that it's a bit too much to do you know
how else to leave the celibate life
happy and so on if you can't quite do
that yet well God descends those
so it is like lowering the requirement
so to speak but even then yeah see God
descends those so that signs and
features see you don't attend to signs
and features you don't see signs and
features you see the thing with your
eyes that has its sort of significance
that has its sort of significance
implications signs and features these
peripheral ideas they come with it
and that's what you don't grasp wrongly
that's what you don't let become your
context carelessly and so on so don't
grasp those signs and features
provocative exactly yeah so then you
would recognize that's where the problem
is of course that's where the last is
so then you guard the doors so the
designs and features will be not
overwhelming you and so that you can
actually understand that's why you need
to stop looking at things that have
provocative signs and features and you
can start chasing them stop going after
just seeing things in different light
well eventually yes yeah like as uh this
woman is like my mother yeah once you
were you were kind of uncoverting that
order of seeing of putting what your
last ones first the context that last
set up first then yes you could realize
oh yeah I could just sustain these
thoughts think about these thoughts and
the mind will go into that direction but
by that point you're already seeing the
mind and mind is on the level of the
signs and features not on the level of
as I said so many times what you're
observing with your senses including
your own thoughts
that you have to think about
and so the King after that he says oh it's
so the King after that he says oh it's
wonderful
how about how how well this has been
stated by the blessed one
so this is the cause and reason why
these young young monks with a blessing
of Youth in the prime of their life have
not played with Central pleasures and
lead the complete pure early life
and he says in my case too when I enter
my harem unguarded in body speech and
mind without setting up mindfulness the
context unrestrained in the sense
faculties on that occasion states have
lost to say only forcefully
but when I enter my harem guarded in
body speech and mind with the context
set up mindfulness setup restrained in
the same faculties on that occasion
states of lust do not to sell me in such
a way
yeah Stephen King had some wisdom while
he was still living with his wives he
had some wisdom there to see for himself
yeah but the root what the root of the
last is what the problem is it's guarded
mind or unguarded mind
it's not behind him
it's not the the objects yeah it's not
the object yeah